Mss.Rec.101 Mss.Rec.101
American Philosophical Society
Okanagan Salish Stories and Songs
1961, 1966, 1971
Mss.Rec.101
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Reel(s)
Okanagan Salish stories with English translations; free conversation on dialectical variations in Okanagan and borrowing from French and English; elicitation sessions covering animal names, fish names, body parts, and words containing fricatives; Catholic hymns in Okanagan and Chinook. Recorded in Penticton, Spectacle Lake, and head of Okanagan Lake, British Columbia, in 1961, 1966, and 1971.
2 sound tape reels (2 hr., 4 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 track, mono; 5 in.
Abel, Mary
Armstrong, Willie
Gabriel, Louise
Gregoire, Tommy
Holding, Margaret
Lezard, George
Pierre, Larry
Pierre, Selina
Watkins, Donald
Related Archival Materials
Project report, letter to APS Librarian, and detailed tape contents available in Phillips Fund Collection (Mss.497.3.Am4).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Donald Watkins in 1975 (Acc. 1975 50.b rec). This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Catholic Church--Prayers and devotions; Chinook jargon; Okanagan Indians--Folklore; Okanagan Indians--Music; Okanagan language; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Prayers and Conversation with Louise, 1971; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:22; Gabriel, Louise; Watkins, Donald
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes prayers: Our Father, Hail Mary, Glory Be, Apostles' Creed. Followed by conversation with selected vocabulary items.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Anthropological linguistics; Catholic Church--Prayers and devotions; Okanagan Indians--Music; Okanagan Indians--Religion; Okanagan language; Penticton (B.C.)
  - Conversation with Larry Pierre with some vocabulary items, 1971; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:14; Pierre, Larry; Watkins, Donald
    A conversation used to establish words containing voiced velar fricatives and pharyngeal fricatives.
    Anthropological linguistics; Okanagan language; Penticton (B.C.)
  - Conversation with Larry Pierre and Willie Armstrong, 1969; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:40; Armstrong, Willie; Pierre, Larry; Watkins, Donald
    Conversation on dialectical variations in Okanagan, borrowings from English and French, and animal and fish names.
    English language--Influence on Okanagan; French language--Influence on Okanagan; Okanagan Indians--Ethnozoology; Okanagan language; Okanagan language--Dialects; Penticton (B.C.)
  - Okanagan word list: Common body parts, 1966; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:41; Pierre, Larry; Watkins, Donald
    Anthropological linguistics; Human body--Terminology; Okanagan language; Penticton (B.C.)
  - Okanagan story, 1966; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:51; Lezard, George; Watkins, Donald
    Story told by George Lezard, an Okanagan monoglot.
    Anthropological linguistics; Okanagan Indians--Folklore; Okanagan language; Penticton (B.C.)
  - Esnéna ecáwc ("The Owl's Affair"), 1971-08; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:02; Gregoire, Tommy; Watkins, Donald
    "The tale of Owl, who kidnapped a boy. Accounts for the origin of the loon and its ghostly call."
    Anthropological linguistics; Loons--Folklore; Okanagan Indian Reserve (B.C.); Okanagan Indians--Folklore; Okanagan language; Owls--Folklore
  - Reaction discussion to Tommy Gregoire's story, 1971-08; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:59; Abel, Joe; Abel, Mary; Watkins, Donald
    Okanagan speech by George Lezard, with inter-sentence translation by Larry Pierre. Topic concerns sources of food and the problem of conflicting cultlures.
  - Story of the old days, 1966; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:51; Lezard, George; Pierre, Larry; Watkins, Donald
    Concerns "sources of food and the problem of conflicting cultures" drawn from the speaker's recollections of a conversation with a Catholic priest.
    Anthropological linguistics; Autobiography; Okanagan Indians--Food; Okanagan Indians--Social life and customs; Okanagan language; Penticton (B.C.)
  - Song: "Communion Hymn", 1961-08-17; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:53; Holding, Margaret; Watkins, Donald
    Recorded at Spectacle Lake in Washington state. Misidentified by collector as being located in British Columbia.
    Anthropological linguistics; Catholic Church--Prayers and devotions; Okanagan Indians--Music; Okanagan Indians--Religion; Okanagan language; Okanogan County (Wash.)
  - Some further examples of Christian hymns sung in Okanagan, 1961; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:21; Holding, Margaret; Watkins, Donald
  - Eagle and Fox, 1966; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:53; Pierre, Larry; Watkins, Donald
    Whole story given first in Okanagan, then in English.
    Anthropological linguistics; Coyote--Folklore; Eagles--Folklore; Okanagan Indians--Folklore; Okanagan language; Penticton (B.C.)
  - Owl, Rabbit, and Chipmunk, 1966; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:13; Pierre, Larry; Pierre, Selina; Watkins, Donald
    Chipmunks--Folklore; Okanagan Indians--Folklore; Okanagan language; Owls--Folklore; Penticton (B.C.); Rabbits--Folklore